<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quickie | Beat of The Geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://\.github.io/\/github/blog/categories/quickie/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://\.github.io/\/github/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-20T09:28:08+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://\.github.io/\/github/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charanjit Singh]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Find which application is running on a particular port]]></title>
    <link href="http://\.github.io/\/github/2014/10/how-to-find-which-application-is-running-on-a-particular-port.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T18:45:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://\.github.io/\/github/2014/10/how-to-find-which-application-is-running-on-a-particular-port</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>I've started two new categories. <code>loud mouth</code> and <code>quickie</code>. I am doing a new experiment of writing a blog post of every new or old (which I haven't documented) I do while I am working on some project. <code>loud mouth</code> is for that. But I don't always like to explain things deep. For those times I am starting <code>quickie</code>, which represents posts which just get stuff done, without explaining much; basically just a dump of the steps I took to solve something. Here's first post that belongs to both these categories.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>I tried a <a href="http://dutzi.github.io/tamper/">Chrome extension</a> I ran into on reddit. It runs mitm proxy behind the screen. Then at an occasion, I had to run a proxy for my work purposes, but I found port 8080 is already taken. It turned out tamper keep mitm proxy running even when it's disabled (not the extension but through the switch given in tamper). This is how I found out which application was using port 8080.</p>

<h2>Use lsof</h2>

<p><code>lsof</code> can be used to check which process owns a particular port</p>

<p><code>lsof -S -i &lt;protocol&gt;:&lt;port&gt;</code> tells which process has the port assigned to it</p>

<p>For example,For example,</p>

<p><code>
lsof -i TCP:8080 -S   
</code></p>

<p>Running above command shows output like this:</p>

<p><code>
Python  15125 channi    3u  IPv4 0xb1b0493c89f7e78f      0t0  TCP *:http-alt (LISTEN)   
</code></p>

<p>Now in next step we can use <code>ps</code> to identify how the Python process with pid <code>15125</code> was started</p>

<h2>Use <code>ps</code></h2>

<p><code>ps</code> can be used to know the command with which the process was executed</p>

<p>From the <code>lsof</code> command we got the pid of the process which owns port 8080. Now we want to know how that process was started so we can have a better idea about the intention of the process.</p>

<p>On Mac OS, we use <code>ps -A | grep 15125</code> for getting that, same command on Linux is <code>ps -aux | grep 15125</code>. <code>15125</code> is the pid of the process we got in previous step using <code>lsof</code></p>

<p>Using <code>ps -A | grep 15125</code> give us this output on OS X:</p>

<p><code>sh
15125 ??         0:59.99 /usr/local/Cellar/python/2.7.8_1/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/2.7/Resources/Python.app/Contents/MacOS/Python /usr/local/bin/tamper.py chrome-extension://mabhojhgigkmnkppkncbkblecnnanfmd/     
25777 ttys002    0:00.00 grep 15125
</code></p>

<p>So now we see the process is started by <code>tamper.py</code> python script which is using <code>Tamper</code> chrome extension.</p>

<p>Tamper is a chrome extension that uses mitm proxy to allow us tamper HTTP(S) requests. So this is not apparently a security breach.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
